盗梦空间
Christopher Nolan's
INCEPTION
Hey! Come here!
快过来
I'm on my way.
马上就来
他已经神志不清了  但还是指名要见你
把他带进来
他身上只带了这个...
还有这个
Are you here to kill me?
你是来杀我的吗
I know what this is.
我知道这是什么
I've seen one before.
很久很久以前
Many, many years ago.
我在一个男人身上见过
It belonged to a man I met
我们在一个梦中相遇
in a half-remembered dream.
而那个梦我已经记不太清了
A man possessed of some radical notions.
那个男人满脑子都是激进的想法
What is the most resilient parasite?
最强大的寄生物是什么
A bacteria? A virus?
是细菌?  是病毒?
An intestinal worm?
还是肠道蠕虫?
What Mr. Cobb is trying to say
柯布先生的意思是...
An idea.
是一个想法
Resilient. Highly contagious.
顽强无比  感染性极强
Once an idea has taken hold of the brain,
你头脑中一旦形成一个想法
it's almost impossible to eradicate.
那就几乎无法抹去
An idea that is fully formed, fully understood,
只要这个想法完整而被理解
that sticks.
就会深深根植在那里
Right in there somewhere.
在大脑里的某个地方
For someone like you to steal?
而你这样的人就来窃取吗
Yes. In the dream state, your conscious defenses are lowered...
对  在梦境中  你的意识会放松警惕
and that makes your thoughts vulnerable to theft.
如此一来你的想法便极易遭到窃取
It's called extraction.
这就叫做盗梦
Mr. Saito, we can train your subconscious to defend itself...
斋藤先生  我们能训练你的潜意识进行自我防御
from even the most skilled extractor.
就算最出色的盗梦者也无计可施
How can you do that?
你凭什么这么肯定
Because I am the most skilled extractor.
因为我就是最出色的盗梦者
I know how to search your mind and find your secrets.
我知道怎样窥探你的想法并找出你的秘密
I know the tricks.
我掌握其中的窍门
And I can teach them to you, so that even when you're asleep...
我能教会你  让你即使在睡着时
your defense is never down.
也绝不会放松警惕
Look, if you want my help,
听着  如果你要我帮忙
you're gonna have to be completely open with me.
就得完全信任我  对我毫无保留
I need to know my way around your thoughts better than your wife...
我得比你的妻子  你的咨询师
better than your therapist, better than anyone.
甚至比任何人  都更了解你的想法
If this is a dream, and you have a safe full of secrets...
如果这是梦  梦里有个藏有你秘密的保险箱
I need to know what's in that safe.
我必须知道保险箱里有什么
In order for this all to work, you need to completely let me in.
为此你必须对我完全坦诚
Enjoy your evening, gentlemen,
祝你们今晚愉快  先生们
as I consider your proposal.
我会考虑一下你们的提议
He knows.
他知道了
What's going on up there?
上面是怎么回事
Saito knows. He's playing with us.
斋藤知道了  他在耍我们
Doesn't matter. I can get it here. Trust me.
无所谓  我能找到它  相信我
The information is in the safe.
情报就在保险箱里
He looked right at it when I mentioned secrets.
我提到秘密时  他下意识地盯着它看
What's she doing here?
她来干什么
Just head back to the room. All right? I'll take care of this.
回房间去吧  这里交给我来处理
Okay, make sure you do. We're here to work.
好吧  你最好处理好  别忘了我们的工作
If I jumped, would I survive?
如果我跳下去  还能活下来吗
With a clean dive, perhaps.
掉进海里的话也许还有希望
Mal, what are you doing here?
玛尔  你在这干什么
I thought you might be missing me.
我以为你会想我
You know that I am.
你知道我想你
But I can't trust you anymore.
但我不能再相信你了
So what?
那又怎样
Looks like Arthur's taste.
看着像是阿瑟的品味
Actually, the subject is partial to postwar British painters.
其实是这次的目标喜欢战后英国画家的作品
Please, have a seat.
请坐吧
Tell me...
告诉我
do the children miss me?
孩子们想我吗
You can't imagine.
想到你无法想象
What are you doing?
你要做什么
Just getting some fresh air.
出去透透新鲜空气
Stay where you are, Mal.
坐那别动  玛尔
God, damn it.
见鬼
Turn around.
转过身来
The gun, Dom.
道姆  把枪放下
Please.
快点
Now the envelope, Mr. Cobb.
把信封交出来  柯布先生
Did she tell you? Or have you known all along?
是她告诉你的呢  还是你本来就知道
That you're here to steal from me, or that we are actually asleep?
知道你是来偷东西的  还是我们其实在做梦
I want to know the name of your employer.
告诉我你雇主的名字
Ah, there's no use threatening him in a dream, right, Mal?
你也知道在梦里威胁他没用吧  玛尔
That depends on what you're threatening.
那得看你怎么威胁了
Killing him would just wake him up.
杀了他只会让他醒过来
But pain...
而疼痛...
Pain is in the mind.
他的大脑会感受到疼痛
And judging by the decor,
从周围的布局来看
we're in your mind, aren't we, Arthur?
我们是在你的梦里吧  阿瑟
What are you doing? It's too soon.
搞什么  你醒得太早了
I know. But the dream's collapsing.
我知道  但梦境崩塌了
I'm gonna try to keep Saito under a little bit longer.
我得尽量让斋藤多留一会
We're almost there.
我们快得手了
He was close. Very close.
他差点就得手了
Stop him!
拦住他
This isn't gonna work. Wake him up.
不起作用  把他叫醒
He won't wake.
他醒不过来
机 密
- Give him the kick. - What?
-让他穿越  -什么
Dunk him.
把他推下去
He's out.
他昏过去了
You came prepared, hmm?
你是有备而来啊
Not even my head of security knows this apartment.
连我的保安主管都不知道这座公寓
How did you find it?
你怎么会知道
It's difficult for a man of your position
像你这种地位的男人
to keep a love nest like this secret...
要保密这样一个爱巢可不容易
particularly where there's a married woman involved.
尤其对方还是有夫之妇
- She would never... - Yet here we are.
-她不可能...  -但事实是  我们在这了
- With a dilemma. - They're getting closer.
-进退两难  -他们慢慢逼近了
- You got what you came for. - Well, that's not true.
-你们已经达到目的了  -并没有
You left out a key piece of information, didn't you?
你把关键部分藏起来了吧
You held something back because you knew what we were up to.
你知道我们的目的  所以有所保留
- Question is, why'd you let us in at all? - An audition.
-但你为何还让我们进来  -算是一次试探
- An audition for what? - Doesn't matter. You failed.
-什么试探  -不重要了  你失败了
We extracted every bit of information you had in there.
我们窃取了你脑中所有的情报
But your deception was obvious.
但你的诡计已被拆穿了
So leave me and go.
放了我  你们走吧
You don't seem to understand, Mr. Saito.
你还不明白吗  斋藤先生
That corporation that hired us, they won't accept failure.
雇佣我们的公司  他们可不允许失败
We won't last two days.
不然我们就死定了
Cobb?
柯布
Looks like I'm gonna have to do this a little more simply.
看来我只能简单粗暴一下了
Tell us what you know!
把你知道的告诉我们
Tell us what you know, now!
快点告诉我们
I've always hated this carpet.
我一直讨厌这条地毯
It's stained and frayed in such distinctive ways.
它褪色和磨损得这么与众不同
But very definitely made of wool.
但好歹是条羊毛毯子
Right now...
可现在...
I'm lying on polyester.
我却躺在一条涤纶毯子上
Which means I'm not lying on my carpet, in my apartment.
也就是说  我不是躺在自己公寓的地毯上
You have lived up to your reputation, Mr. Cobb.
你果然不负盛名  柯布先生
I'm still dreaming.
我依然在做梦
- How'd it go? - Not good.
-进展如何  -不太妙
Dream within a dream, huh? I'm impressed.
梦中有梦  真是佩服
But in my dream, you play by my rules.
但在我梦里  得由我说了算
Ah, yes, but you see, Mr. Saito...
这么说吧  斋藤先生...
We're not in your dream.
我们不是在你的梦里
We're in mine.
而是在我的梦里
Asshole. How do you mess up the carpet?
蠢货  你怎么会把地毯搞错
- It wasn't my fault. - You're the architect.
-那不是我的错  -你可是造梦师
I didn't know he was gonna rub his cheek on it!
我怎么知道他会把他揍得贴在地毯上
That's enough.
别吵了
You. What the hell was all that?
还有你  你究竟在搞什么
- I have it under control. - I'd hate to see you out of control.
-我控制住了局势  -是么  那失控岂不是更夸张
We don't have time for this. I'm getting off at Kyoto.
没时间争论了  我要在京都下车
Why? He's not gonna check every compartment.
怎么  他又不会查看每节车厢
Yeah, well, I don't like trains.
没错  但我不喜欢坐火车
Listen. Every man for himself.
听好  各自保重吧
Yes, hello?
你好
- Hi, Daddy. - Hi, Dad.
-爸爸  -爸爸
Hey, guys. Hey. How are you? How you doing, huh?
小鬼们  你们好吗  过得怎样
- Good. - Okay, I guess.
-很好  -还好吧
Okay? Who's just okay? Is that you, James?
还好吧  这是谁在说话  是你吗  詹姆斯
Yeah. When are you coming home, Dad?
是我  爸爸  你什么时候回家
Well, I can't, sweetheart. I can't.
不行  亲爱的  我不能回家
Not for a while, remember?
还得一阵子  记得吗
Why?
为什么
Look, I told you, I'm away because I'm working, right?
我说过了  我要工作  不能回家
Grandma says you're never coming back.
外婆说你再也不会回来了
Phillipa, is that you?
菲丽帕  是你吗
Put Grandma on the phone for me, will you?
让外婆听电话好吗
She's shaking her head.
她在摇头
Well, just hope she's wrong about that.
那我们只能希望她错了
Daddy?
爸爸
Yeah, James?
怎么了  詹姆斯
Is Mommy with you?
妈妈和你在一起吗
James, we talked about this.
詹姆斯  我们谈过了
Mommy's not here anymore.
妈妈已经不在这了
Where?
那她在哪里
That's enough, kids. Say bye-bye.
好了  孩子们  说再见吧
Listen, I'm gonna send some presents with Grandpa, all right?
听着  我会让外公带些礼物回去  好吗
And you be good, you be...
你们要听话...
- Our ride's on the roof. - Right.
-直升机就在房顶  -好
Hey, are you okay?
你没事吧
Yeah. Yeah, I'm fine. Why?
我很好  怎么了
Well, down in the dream, Mal showing up.
我们在梦里时  玛尔出现了
Look, I'm, uh, sorry about your leg.
很抱歉她开枪打了你的腿
Won't happen again.
不会再这样了
It's getting worse, isn't it?
情况越来越糟了吧
One apology's all you're getting, all right, Arthur?
我们就事论事好吧  阿瑟
- Where's Nash? - He hasn't shown. You wanna wait?
-纳什人呢  -他还没来  要等他吗
We were supposed to deliver Saito's expansion plans...
我们早该在2小时前就把斋藤的扩建计划
to Cobol Engineering two hours ago
交给科博尔工程公司
By now, they know we failed.
现在他们肯定知道我们失败了
It's time we disappear.
我们得赶紧消失
- Where you gonna go? - Buenos Aires.
-你要去哪里  -布宜诺斯艾利斯
I can lie low there,
在那里避一阵风头
maybe sniff out a job when things quiet down. You?
等风平浪静了没准还能揽个活  你呢
Stateside.
回美国
Send my regards.
代我问候你家人
He sold you out. Thought to come to me and bargain for his life.
他出卖了你们  跑来求我饶他一命
So I offer you the satisfaction.
现在我交给你们处理
It's not the way I deal with things.
这不是我的做事风格
- What will you do with him? - Nothing.
-你要对他怎么样  -没什么
But I can't speak for Cobol Engineering.
但科博尔公司就难说了
- What do you want from us? - Inception.
-你想要我们做什么  -植梦
- Is it possible? - Of course not.
-可能吗  -当然不可能
If you can steal an idea from someone's mind...
你要是能从别人脑中窃取想法
why can't you plant one there instead?
为何不能反过来植入一个念头
Okay, here's me planting an idea in your head.
好吧  现在我来对你植入一个想法
I say, "Don't think about elephants".
我说  "不要去想大象"
What are you thinking about?
你会想到什么
Elephants.
大象
Right. But it's not your idea,
没错  但这不是你的想法
because you know I gave it to you.
因为你知道是我灌输给你的
The subject's mind can always trace the genesis of the idea.
目标的大脑总能追溯想法的来源
- True inspiration's impossible to fake. - That's not true.
-不可能假造真实的想法来源  -那不一定
- Can you do it? - Are you offering me a choice?
-你能做到吗  -你是在给我选择吗
Because I can find my own way to square things with Cobol.
因为我自己有办法摆平科博尔的麻烦
Then you do have a choice.
那你自己选择吧
Then I choose to leave, sir.
那我选择离开  先生
Tell the crew where you want to go.
告诉机组你的目的地
Hey, Mr. Cobb.
柯布先生
How would you like to go home,to America, to your children?
如果让你回家  回到美国的孩子身边  你看怎样
You can't fix that. No one can.
这你做不到  没人可以
- Just like inception. - Cobb, come on.
-比植梦还难吗  -柯布  走吧
- How complex is the idea? - Simple enough.
-这个想法有多复杂  -相当简单
No idea is simple when you need to plant it
任何想在别人脑中植入的想法
in somebody else's mind.
都不可能简单
My main competitor is an old man in poor health.
我的主要竞争对手是个病入膏肓的老人
His son will soon inherit control of the corporation.
他的儿子马上就要继承他的公司
I need him to decide to break up his father's empire.
我要他决定解散他父亲的商业帝国
- Cobb, we should walk away from this. - Hold on.
-柯布  我们应该远离这种纷争  -先等一下
If I were to do this, if I even could do it...
如果我愿意干  如果我确实做到了
I'd need a guarantee.
我需要你的保证
- How do I know you can deliver? - You don't.
-我怎么确定你能做到  -你别无选择
But I can.
只能相信我
So do you want to take a leap of faith...
那么你是想放手一搏
or become an old man, filled with regret...
还是变成一个老人  心中充满悔恨
waiting to die alone?
孤零零地等死
Assemble your team, Mr. Cobb.
集结你的团队吧  柯布先生
And choose your people more wisely.
这次可要慎重挑选队友了
Look, I know how much you wanna go home.
我知道你有多想回家
This can't be done.
但这活我们干不了
Yes, it can.
不  可以
Just have to go deep enough.
只要潜入得足够深
You don't know that.
你没法确定
I've done it before.
我以前做过
Who'd you do it to?
是对谁
Why are we going to Paris?
我们为什么去巴黎
We're gonna need a new architect.
我们需要一个新的造梦师
You never did like your office, did you?
你从来不喜欢你的办公室吧
No space to think in that broom cupboard.
那个地方小得根本没法思考
Is it safe for you to be here?
你来这里安全吗
Extradition between France and the United States...
你也知道  法国和美国间的引渡条款
is a bureaucratic nightmare, you know that.
简直就是官僚主义的噩梦
I think they might find a way
说不定就你这个案子
to make it work in your case.
他们会想办法破个例
Look, I, uh, brought these for you to...
我买了一些东西
give to the kids when you have a chance.
你有机会就带给孩子们吧
It'll take more than the occasional stuffed animal...
时不时地送点绒毛玩具
to convince those children they still have a father.
这样做爸爸可不行
I'm just doing what I know.
我只是尽我所能
I'm doing what you taught me.
这些都是你教我的
I never taught you to be a thief.
我从没教你去偷东西
No, you taught me to navigate people's minds.
没错  你教我如何引导别人的思想
But after what happened...
但在那件事以后...
there weren't a whole lot of legitimate ways
几乎就没什么合法的机会
for me to use that skill.
能让我发挥这种技能了
What are you doing here, Dom?
道姆  你来这做什么
I think I found a way home.
我想我找到回家的方法了
It's a job for some very, very powerful people.
只要为一些权高位重的人干上一票
People who I believe can fix my charges permanently.
我相信他们能彻底撤销对我的指控
But I need your help.
但我需要你的帮助
You're here to corrupt one of my brightest and best.
你是来带坏我最好的学生吗
You know what I'm offering.
你知道的 我提供的条件很优越
Let them decide for themselves.
你得让他们自己决定
- Money. - Not just money.
-钱吗  -不仅仅是钱
You remember.
你也知道
It's the chance to
那会让我们有机会
build cathedrals, entire cities...
建造大教堂 整座城市...
things that never existed...
创造那些现实中从未存在过
things that couldn't exist in the real world.
也绝不可能存在的事物
So you want me to let someone else
所以你想要我找个人
follow you into your fantasy?
跟你一起走进你的幻想
They don't actually come into the dream.
他们不必亲自进入梦境
They just design the levels
他们只需设计梦境
and teach them to the dreamers. That's all.
再把详情教给梦主就行
Design it yourself.
你自己设计好了
Mal won't let me.
玛尔会阻止我
Come back to reality, Dom.
回到现实中来吧  道姆
- Please. - Reality.
-求你了  -现实
Those kids, your grandchildren...
我的孩子  也就是你的外孙...
they're waiting for their father to come back home.
正等着他们的父亲回家
That's their reality.
对他们来说这才是现实
And this job, this last job,
而只有完成这最后一次任务
that's how I get there.
我才能实现这个愿望
I would not be standing here if I knew any other way.
如果不是走投无路  我绝不会来这求你
I need an architect who's as good as I was.
我需要个和我一样出色的造梦师
I've got somebody better.
比你更出色
Ariadne?
阿里阿德涅
I'd like you to meet Mr. Cobb.
这位是柯布先生
Pleased to meet you.
很高兴见到你
If you have a few moments,
如果你有时间
Mr. Cobb has a job offer.
柯布先生有份工作给你
He'd like to discuss with you.
他想和你聊几句
A work placement?
实习吗
Not exactly.
也不算
I have a test for you.
我要先测试一下你
You're not gonna tell me anything first?
你不先告诉我是什么工作吗
Before I describe the job, I have to know you can do it.
在这之前  我得确认你能够胜任
- Why? - It's not, strictly speaking, legal.
-为什么  -严格来说  这并不合法
You have two minutes to design a maze
给你两分钟时间  设计一个
that it takes one minute to solve.
花一分钟才能解开的迷宫
Stop.
时间到
Again.
再来
Stop.
时间到
You're gonna have to do better than that.
这都太简单了
That's more like it.
这才像话
They say we only use a fraction of our brain's true potential.
都说我们只开发了大脑真正潜力的一小部分
Now, that's when we're awake.
但这只是在我们醒着的时候
When we're asleep, our mind can do almost anything.
当睡着时  我们的大脑几乎无所不能
Such as?
比如呢
Imagine you're designing a building.
想象一下  你设计一座建筑物时
You consciously create each aspect.
你有意识地设计出每个部分
But sometimes, it feels like it's almost creating itself,
但有时却感觉像是建筑在自行构建
if you know what I mean.
明白我的意思吗
Yeah, like I'm discovering it.
对  我只需要去发现而已
Genuine inspiration, right?
纯粹的灵感  是吧
Now, in a dream, our mind continuously does this.
而在梦里  大脑会连续地保持这样
We create and perceive our world simultaneously.
创造和感知  这两个过程同步发生
And our mind does this so well
而我们的大脑是如此神奇
that we don't even know it's happening.
以至于我们自己根本没意识到
That allows us to get right in the middle of that process.
这么一来我们就能直接进入这个过程
- How? - By taking over the creating part.
-怎么做  -由我们来创造
Now, this is where I need you.
这就是你的工作
You create the world of the dream.
你创造一个梦境
We bring the subject into that dream,
我们把目标带入这个梦境
and they fill it with their subconscious.
这个梦境里则会充满他们的潜意识
How could I ever acquire enough detail
一个梦境的细节要有多逼真
to make them think that it's reality?
才能让对方相信自己身处现实
Well, dreams, they feel real while we're in them, right?
我们做梦时总是感觉很真实吧
It's only when we wake up
只有等我们醒来后
that we realize something was actually strange.
才会意识到不对劲
Let me ask you a question.
问你个问题吧
You never really remember the beginning of a dream, do you?
你从不记得梦的开头，是吧
You always wind up right in the middle of what's going on.
总是突然就这么置身其中
I guess, yeah.
我想是吧
So how did we end up here?
那我们是怎么来这的
Well, we just came from the, uh...
我们刚从...
Think about it, Ariadne. How did you get here?
仔细想想  阿里阿德涅  你怎么来这的
Where are you right now?
你现在哪里
We're dreaming?
我们在做梦吗
You're in the middle of the workshop, sleeping.
你其实正在一个车间里睡觉
This is your first lesson in shared dreaming. Stay calm.
这是你分享梦境的第一课  冷静
If it's just a dream, then why are you covering...
如果这只是做梦  你为什么要遮挡...
Because it's never just a dream, is it?
因为这绝不仅仅只是个梦
And a face full of glass hurts like hell.
玻璃刺在脸上的感觉生疼
When you're in it, it feels real.
你做梦时  感觉是真实的
That's why the military developed dream sharing.
所以军队开发了分享梦境系统
It was a training program for soldiers to shoot,
士兵能通过这个程序
stab and strangle each other...
身临其境地射击  格斗和搏杀
and then wake up.
而不会受到伤害
How did architects become involved?
造梦师的工作是什么
Well, someone had to design the dreams, right?
总得有人去设计梦境吧
Why don't you give us another five minutes?
再给我们五分钟吧
Five minutes?
五分钟
What? We were talking for, like, at least an hour.
怎么会  我们少说也谈了一个小时
In a dream, your mind functions more quickly...
你做梦时  大脑运转速度加快
therefore time seems to feel more slow.
所以时间相对变慢
Five minutes in the real world gives you an hour in the dream.
现实中的五分钟  相当于梦境里的一小时
Why don't you see what you can get up to in five minutes?
何不看看你在五分钟内能做些什么
You've got the basic layout. Bookstore, cafe?
基本布局有了  书店  咖啡店
Almost everything else is here too.
该有的东西差不多都有了
- Who are the people? - Projections of my subconscious.
-这些人是谁  -我潜意识中的映射
- Yours? - Yes.
-你的吗  -对
Remember, you are the dreamer. You build this world.
记住  你是梦主  你创造了梦境
I am the subject. My mind populates it.
而我是目标  梦境里充满了我的潜意识
You can literally talk to my subconscious.
你还可以和我的潜意识交谈
That's one of the ways we extract information from the subject.
这也是盗取目标秘密的方法之一
How else do you do it?
除此之外呢
By creating something secure,
你可以设计一个安全场所
like a bank vault or a jail.
比如银行金库  或是监狱
The mind automatically fills it with information it's trying to protect.
重要信息就会自动存入其中
You understand?
明白了吗
- Then you break in and steal it? - Well...
-你再潜入梦境去偷吗  -这个嘛...
I guess I thought that the dream's space should be all about the visual,
我本以为梦境该基于视觉
but it's more about the feel of it.
但其实更重要的是去感觉
My question is what happens when you
我想知道  如果我
start messing with the physics of it all?
颠覆了物理规律  会有什么后果
- It's something, isn't it? - Yes, it is.
-很厉害吧  -是啊
Why are they all looking at me?
他们为什么都看着我
Because my subconscious feels that someone else is creating this world.
因为我的潜意识觉得这是别人创造的梦境
The more you change things,
你改建得越离谱
the quicker the projections start to converge on you.
映射就会越早如潮水般涌向你
Converge?
涌向我?
They sensed the foreign nature of the dreamer.
他们一旦察觉外来入侵的梦主
They attack like white blood cells fighting an infection.
就会像白血球抵抗感染那般攻击对方
Are they gonna attack us?
他们会攻击我们吗
No, actually, just you.
不  只攻击你
This is great. But I'm telling you,
这样很棒  但我也说了
if you keep changing things like this...
如果你再这么继续下去...
Gees! Mind telling your subconscious to take it easy?
受不了  就不能让你的潜意识冷静点么
It's my subconscious, remember, I can't control it.
这可是我的潜意识  我没法控制的
Very impressive.
佩服
I know this bridge. This place is real, isn't it?
我认识这座桥  这是真实存在的吧
Yeah, I cross it everyday to get to the college.
对  我每天穿过桥去学校
Never recreate places from your memory,
绝不能重建你记忆里的场景
always imagine new places.
必须创造新的东西
Well, you gotta draft from stuff you know, right?
你总得借用熟悉的东西吧
Only use details, uh...
只能借用细节...
A street lamp, or a phone booth, never entire areas.
比如路灯啊电话亭啊  但绝不能复制整块地方
Why not?
为什么
Because building a dream from your memory...
因为借用记忆中的场景塑造梦境
is the easiest way to lose your grasp on  what's real and what is a dream.
极易让你迷失何为梦境何为现实
- Is that what happened to you? - Listen to me,
-你有过这种经历吗  -听着
this has nothing to do with me, understand?
这和我无关  懂吗
Is that why you need me to build your dreams?
所以你要我来帮你造梦吗
Get off of her. Back off.
放开她  走开
- Back off! - No!
-滚开  -别碰我
Get off of her!
别碰她
Mal!
玛尔
Wake me up! Wake me up!
把我叫醒  快把我叫醒
Mal! Mal!
玛尔
Wake me up! Wake me up!
把我叫醒
Hey, hey, hey! Look at me. You're okey? You're okey?
看着我  你没事了  没事了
Why... why wouldn't I wake up?
为什么我醒不过来
Because there was still some time on the clock,
因为设定的时间还没到
and you can't wake up within a dream unless you die.
除非你在梦里死去  不然没法提前醒来
- She'll need a totem. - What?
-她需要个图腾  -什么
A totem is a small personal...
图腾是个小的私人...
That's some subconscious you've got in you, Cobb.
你的潜意识可真厉害啊  柯布
She's a real charmer!
还是个大美女呢
Oh, I see you met Mrs. Cobb.
看来你见过柯布夫人了
- She's his wife? - Yeah. So... a totem,
-那是他妻子吗  -对  话说图腾...
you need a small object potentially heavy,
你需要一个小巧的物件
something could have on you all the time
能够一直带在身边
- that no one else knows. - Like a coin?
-不能让别人知道  -像硬币吗
No, it must be more unique than that.
不  得更独特才行
This is a loaded die.
这是一个注铅的骰子
No, I can't let you touch it, that would defeat the purpose.
不  你不能碰  不然就没意义了
Only I know the balance and the weight of this particular loaded die.
只有我知道这个特制骰子的重心和重量
That way, when you look at your totem,
只有这样  当你看着自己的图腾
you know, beyond a doubt, that you're not in someone else's dream.
你才能确信自己不在别人的梦里
I... I don't know...
我不知道...
if you can't see what's going on, or if you just don't want to,
你是不想知道还是的确不知道
but Cobb has some serious problems that he's tried to bury down there.
柯布的内心深处隐藏着很严重的问题
And I'm not about to just open my mind to someone like that.
我可不想对这种人敞开心扉
She'll be back.
她会回来的
I've never seen anyone pick it up that quickly before.
我还从没见过有人能学得这么快
Reality is not gonna be enough for her now.
现实已经不能满足她了
When she comes back...
当她回来时...
when she comes back, you're gonna help her building mazes.
你就教她设计迷宫
- Where're you gonna be? - I gotta go visit Eames.
-那你呢  -我要去找伊姆斯
Eames? Now he's in Mombasa.
伊姆斯  他在蒙巴萨
It's Cobol's backyard.
那里可是科博尔公司的老巢
It's a necessary risk.
必须冒这个险
There's plenty of good thieves.
神偷多了去了
We don't just need a thief. We need a forger.
我们不仅需要小偷  我们需要个伪装者
You can rub them together all you want, they're not gonna breed.
你再怎么搓也生不出钱来
You never know.
那可不一定
I'll get you a drink.
去喝一杯吧
You're buying.
你请客
- Your spelling hasn't improved. - Piss off.
-你的拼写还是这么差  -去你的
- How's your handwriting? - Versatile.
-书写怎么样了  -信手拈来
- Good. - Thank you very much.
-那就好  -多谢
Inception.
植入思想
Now, before you bother telling me it's impossible...
在你费心告诉我这不可能前...
No, it's perfectly possible. It's just bloody difficult.
这当然可能  只是难得要死
Just difficult?
只是难吗
Arthur keeps telling me it can't be done.
阿瑟总说这不可能
Hmm... Arthur. You're still working with that stick-in-the-mud?
哈  阿瑟  你还和那个榆木脑袋在一起么
He's good at what he does, right?
作为前哨来说他很优秀  是吧
Oh, the best. He has no imagination.
是最优秀的  只是缺乏想象力
- Not like you. - Listen, if you wanna perform inception,
-你就不同  -听着  如果你要植梦
- you need imagination. - Let me ask you something,
-必须要有想象力  -问你个问题
- have you done it before? - We tried it.
-你以前做过吗  -我们试过
We got the idea in place, but it didn't take.
想法都就位了  但对方没有上钩
You didn't plant it deep enough?
你们植入得不够深吗
It's not just about depth, you know...
这不只是深度问题
you need the simplest version of the idea,
植入的想法必须极其简单
in order it to grow naturally in the subject's mind.
让目标觉得这是自然而生的想法
That's a very subtle art.
这可是相当微妙的艺术
So what is this idea that you need to plant?
你要植入的想法是什么
We need the heir of a major corporation
我们要让一个大公司的继承人
to dissolve his father's empire.
决定瓦解他父亲的企业帝国
Well, you see right there, you have various political motivations of...
这么说吧  关于反垄断的看法
anti-monopolistic sentiments and so forth, and all of that stuff.
有各种各样的政治动机  诸如此类
That's all.
但是所有的一切
It's really at the mercy of your subject's prejudice, you see?
最终还是取决于目标的偏好  明白吗
All you have to do is to start with the absolute basic.
你只须着眼于最基本的东西
- Which is what? - The relationship with the father.
-是什么  -他和父亲之间的关系
- Do you have a chemist? - No, not yet.
-你有药剂师了吗  -还没有
Alright.
那好
Okey, there's a man here, Yusuf Pierro.
这儿有个人  叫尤瑟夫・皮耶罗
He formulates his own versions of the compounds.
他配制的药剂独一无二
When are you taking me there?
你什么时候带我去见见
Once you've lost your tail.
你先甩掉跟踪你的人吧
Man at the bar.
吧台边的那家伙
Cobol engineering.
科博尔公司的
That price on my head, was that "dead or alive?"
对我的悬赏要求是死是活
I don't remember. Let's see if he starts shooting.
不记得了  看他开不开枪吧
Run interference, I'll meet you downstairs in the bar in, say uh...
你替我引开他  我们半小时后
say half an hour?
酒吧楼下见吧
- Be back here? - It's the last place they'd expect.
-再回到这里吗  -最危险的地方最安全
Hum-hmm. Well...
好吧
Freddy, Freddy Savens?
弗雷迪  你是弗雷迪・赛文斯吗
My God, it's you, isn't it?
天啊  真的是你吗
No, it isn't.
看来我认错人了
You're not dreaming now, are you?
这下你不是在做梦了吧
There!
那边
Okey.
没事
Oh, uh... cafe. One... one cafe.
咖啡  要一杯咖啡
One cafe.
一杯咖啡
Care for a lift, Mr. Cobb?
要搭车么  柯布先生
What're you doing here in Mombasa?
你怎么会在蒙巴萨
I need to protect my investments.
我得保护我的投资对象
Ahh, so this is your idea of losing a tail, uh?
甩个人就这么难吗
Different tail.
还有一伙人
Cobb said you'd be back.
柯布说过你会回来
I tried not to come. But...
我也不想  但...
But there's nothing quite like it.
你已经无法自拔了
It's just... pure creation.
只是...纯粹的创造
Shall we take a look at some paradoxical architecture?
我们来看一些矛盾建筑吧
You're gonna have to master a few tricks,
如果你要建造三层不同的梦境
if you're gonna build three complete dream levels.
就得掌握一些窍门
Excuse me.
抱歉
What kind of tricks?
什么样的窍门
In a dream, you can cheat architecture into impossible shapes.
在梦里  你可以把建筑设计成不可能图形
That lets you create closed loops,
这样你就能造出闭合的循环
like the Penrose steps, the infinite staircases.
好比彭罗斯阶梯  无止尽的阶梯
See?
看见了吗
Paradox.
矛盾建筑
So a closed loop like that will help you
这样的闭合循环
disguise the boundaries of the dream you create.
有助你分辨梦境的边缘
But how big do these levels have to be?
梦境的每一层需要多大
It could be anything from the floor of a building to an entire city.
随你  一个楼面 一幢大楼或是一座城市
But they have to be complicated
但梦境必须非常复杂
enough that we can hide from the projections.
能让我们躲避映射的追踪
A maze?
比如一个迷宫吗
Right, a maze, and the better the maze...
对  迷宫  迷宫越好...
Then the longer we have before the projections catch us?
映射就越难找到我们吗
- Exactly. - My subconscious seems polite enough.
-没错  -我的潜意识看来挺有礼貌
You wait, they'll turn ugly.
等着瞧  他们也会翻脸不认人
No one likes to feel someone else messing around in their mind.
没人喜欢别人在自己的大脑里乱窜
Cobb can't build anymore, can he?
柯布不能再造梦了吧
I don't know if he can't, but he won't.
就算他可以  他也不愿意了
He thinks it's safer if he doesn't know the layouts.
他觉得他不知道梦境的话会更保险
Why?
为什么
He won't tell me. I think it's Mal.
他不愿意说  我想是因为玛尔吧
- His ex-wife? - No, not his ex.
-他前妻吗  -不  不是
- They're still together? - No, she...
-他们还在一起吗  -不  她...
she's dead.
她已经死了
What you just see in there is just his projection of her.
你看到的她不过是他脑中的映射
- What was she like in real life? - She was lovely.
-她在现实中怎么样  -她很迷人
- You're seeking a chemist? - Yes.
-你要找药剂师吗  -对
To formulate compounds for a job.
任务需要配制药剂吗
And to go into the field with us.
还得和我们一起进入梦境
No, I rarely go into the field, Mr. Cobb.
不  我从不进入梦境  柯布先生
We need you there to tailor compounds specific to our needs.
你得在梦里根据需要定做药剂
- Which are? - Great depth.
-有什么要求  -足够深度
A dream within a dream? two levels?
梦中梦吗  两层梦境
- Three. - Not possible.
-三层  -这不可能
That many dreams within dreams is too unstable.
这种多层梦境太不稳定了
It is possible. You just have to add a sedative.
有可能  只需要加镇静剂
A powerful sedative.
强效镇静剂
- How many team members? - Five.
-一共几个人  -五个
Six.
六个
The only way to know you've done the job
只有我和你们一起进入梦境
is if I go in with you.
才能确定你是否完成了任务
There's no room for tourists on a job like this,
这种工作可不能带观光客
Mr. Saito.
斋藤先生
This time it seems there is.
那这次得破例了
This, I think, is a good place to start. I use it everyday.
先试试这个吧  我每天都用
- What for? - Here, I'll show you.
-用来做什么  -来  我带你看看
- Perhaps, you will not want to see. - After you.
-你得做好心理准备  -你先请
Ten... twelve, all connected.
十个...十二个  全部连在一起
Bloody hell!
天啊
They come here everyday to share the dream.
他们每天来这分享梦境
You see? Very stable.
看见了吗  非常稳定
- How long do they dream for? - Three, four hours, each day.
-他们每天做梦多久  -三四个小时吧
- And the dream time? - With this compound?
-梦里是多久  -在这种药效下
About 40 hours, each and every day.
每人每天四十个小时
Why do they do it?
他们为什么这么做
Tell him, Mr. Cobb.
你来说吧  柯布先生
After a while,
在你用药一阵子后
it becomes the only way you can dream.
不用药就没法做梦了
Do you still dream, Mr. Cobb?
你还做梦吗  柯布先生
They come here everyday to sleep?
他们每天来这做梦吗
No, they come to be woken up.
不  他们是为了醒过来
The dream has become their reality. Who are you to say otherwise, uh?
梦境已成了他们的现实  谁又能说不是呢
Let's see what you can do.
让我见识一下吧
You know how to find me. You know what you have to do.
你知道怎么找到我  你知道你该怎么做
Sharp? No?
够劲吧
Are you all right, Mr. Cobb?
你没事吧  柯布先生
Yeah, yeah. I'm just fine.
放心  我没事
Robert Fischer,
罗伯特・费舍尔
heir to the Fischer-Morrow Energy Conglomerate.
费舍尔明日能源集团的继承人
What's your problem with this Mr. Fischer?
你和这位费舍尔先生有何瓜葛
That's not your concern.
这不关你的事
Mr. Saito, this...
斋藤先生  这...
this isn't your typical corporate espionage.
这可不是一般的商业间谍活动
You asked me for inception, I do hope you understand that...
你让我植梦  我希望你明白...
the gravity of that request.
这其中的严重性
The seed that we plant in this man's mind will grow into an idea.
我们会在对方脑中植入一个想法
This idea would define him. It may come to change...
这个想法会决定他的行为
it may come to change everything about him.
可能会彻底改变他的人生
We're the last company standing between them and total energy dominance.
我们是仅存的能和他们抗衡的能源公司
We can no longer compete.
但我们快撑不住了
Soon they'll control the energy supply of half the world.
很快他们将控制半个世界的能源供给
In effect, they become a new superpower.
事实上  他们将成为新兴超级帝国
The world needs Robert Fischer
全世界都需要罗伯特・费舍尔
to change his mind.
改变主意
That's where we come in.
这要看我们的了
How is Robert Fischer's
罗伯特・费舍尔
relationship with his father?
和他父亲的关系如何
Rumor is their relationship is quite complicated.
传言他们之间的关系有些复杂
But we can't work based solely on rumor, can we?
但光靠传言可不够  是吧
Can you get me access to this man here,
你能让我接近这个男人吗
Browning?
布朗宁
Fischer senior's right-hand man,
老费舍尔的左膀右臂
Fischer junior's godfather.
小费舍尔的教父
It should be possible, if you can get the right references.
应该不难  只要你有合适的推荐信
References are something of a speciality for me, Mr. Saito.
搞推荐信可是我的专长  斋藤先生
I'm not smelling settlement here.
这里还有未解决的事项
- Take them down. - Mr. Browning,
-去搞定它  -布朗宁先生
Maurice Fischer's policy is always one of
莫里斯・费舍尔的原则之一
avoiding litigation.
就是避免一切诉讼
Well, shall we voice your concerns
那我们是不是应该把你的想法
with Maurice directly?
直接告诉莫里斯
Not sure if that's necessary.
没那个必要吧
No, no, no. I think we should.
不  我觉得有必要
How is he?
他怎么样了
I don't wanna bother him unnecessarily, but...
我也不想因琐事而麻烦他  但...
Robert, I've told you to
罗伯特  我告诉过你
keep out the damn...
别让那些该死的...
Just do it!
照做就是了
No, don't speak, Mr. Fischer.
你不适合讲话  费舍尔先生
Never... never do thing what I asked.
总是不照我说的做
Leave town.
出去吧
Must be a cherished memory of this.
这一定是他宝贵的回忆
I put it beside his bed. He hasn't even noticed it.
我把相框放在他床边  他甚至都没注意到
Robert, we need to talk about the power of attorney.
罗伯特  我们得谈谈委托书的问题了
I know this is hard for you...
我知道现在不合适...
Not now, uncle Peter.
现在不行  彼得叔叔
But it's imperative that we start to...
但刻不容缓  我们得开始...
The vultures are circling.
秃鹰在盘旋
It is the sicker Maurice Fischer becomes,
莫里斯・费舍尔病得越重
The more powerful Peter Browning becomes.
彼得・布朗宁就越强大
I've had ample opportunity to observe Browning,
我充分观察了布朗宁
adopt his physical presence, study his mannerisms, so on and so forth.
记下了他的模样  行为模式和习惯等等
So now, in the first layer of the dream,
所以在梦境的第一层
I can impersonate Browning,
我可以模仿布朗宁
and suggest the concept to Fischer's conscious mind.
并给费舍尔的大脑灌输暗示
Then, when we take him a level deeper,
当我们带他进入更深一层
his own projection of Browning should...
他脑中产生的布朗宁的映射
should feed that right back to him.
会把这些信息反馈给他自己
- So he gives himself the idea? - Precisely.
-让他觉得这是自己的想法  -没错
That's the only way it will stick. It has to seem self-generated.
只能这么做  必须是自发生成的想法
Eames, I am impressed.
伊姆斯  不错嘛
Your condescension, as always,
能得到你的赞赏
is much appreciated, Arthur. Thank you.
我真是受宠若惊  阿瑟  感激不尽
Were you going under on your own?
你一个人进入梦境吗
No, no. I was just, uh...  just running some experiments.
不  我就是做些实验
I didn't realize anyone was here. So...
没想到这里还有人  所以...
Yeah, I was just... I was working on my totem, actually.
嗯  其实我在弄我的图腾
Here, let me take a look.
给我看看
So you're learning, huh?
你学得还真快
An elegant solution for keeping track of reality.
这种鉴别现实的方法好别致啊
- Was it your idea? - No, it was, uh...
-是你的主意吗  -不  其实...
It was Mal's, actually. This is...
其实是玛尔的主意  这个...
This one was hers.
这个陀螺以前是她的
She'd spin it in a dream and it would never topple,
陀螺在梦里转起来就不会倒
just spin and spin.
就这么一直转下去
Arthur told me she passed away.
听阿瑟说她去世了
How are the mazes coming along?